Register of the Jakub Berman papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Jakub Berman papers
1941-1983
2008C88
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Memoirs, other speeches and writings, notes, correspondence, and photographs relating to the Polish communist movement and to post-World War II political conditions in Poland.
Berman, Jakub, 1901-1984.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collections
Stefan Jędrychowski papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Roman Zambrowski papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Henryk Jablonski papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Edward Osóbka-Morawski papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
Jakub Berman was born in 1901 in Warsaw into a Jewish middle-class family. He completed a degree in law at Warsaw University in 1925. Three years later he joined the Polish Communist Party (KPP). After the Nazi-Soviet attack and partition of Poland in September 1939, Berman moved to the Soviet side of Poland. Initially, he worked as a newspaper editor and later became an instructor in the Comintern school, which trained activists for Josef Stalin's new party for Polish communists, the Polish Workers' Party.
Stalin was favorably impressed with Berman's intellectual abilities and political commitment during meetings in the Kremlin in 1943. In the summer of 1944, as the Soviet armies were driving the Germans out of occupied Poland, Berman became a Politburo member, second only to Boleslaw Bierut, an ethnic Pole of peasant origin, chosen by Stalin to lead the new Polish state. Between 1944 and 1956, during which he was a member of the Polska Zjednoczona Partia Robotnicza Biuro Polityczne, Berman was one of the most powerful Polish communist politicians. Berman's responsibilities in the Politburo included oversight of the Security Office (UB), ideology, and propaganda. During his tenure at least 200,000 people were imprisoned for real or imagined political offenses, of whom some 6,000 were executed.
During the relative political "thaw" following the deaths of Stalin in 1953 and Bierut in 1956, Berman was forced to resign from the Politburo and the Central Committee. He was officially blamed for "Stalinist errors and deviations" but never prosecuted. His name is associated with the Sovietization of Poland following World War II and repressions against the opponents of the communist regime. Berman died in retirement in Warsaw in 1984.
Scope and Content of Collection
Memoirs, other speeches and writings, notes, correspondence, and photographs relating to the Polish communist movement and the Polish People's Republic, post-World War II political conditions in Poland, and the Sovietization of Eastern Europe.
Communism--Poland.; Polska Zjednoczona Partia Robotnicza.; Poland--Politics and government--1945-1980.
- Biographical file, communist party identity cards (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Correspondence
  - General, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Dzierzynska (Dzherzinska), Zofia, 1942-1950 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Kasman, L. A., 1942-1943 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Schaff, Adam, 1955 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Memoirs
  - General, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Testimony for the Ministry of Foreign Affairs archives, 1983 (Box-folder 1: 7)
- Notes
  - General (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - 1948 (Box-folder 1: 9)
- Subject File
  - Centralne Biuro Komunistow Polskich (Central Bureau of the Polish Communists), 1944 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Communist Party of the Soviet Union, Information Bureau - plans to dissolve, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Commintern, school of, 1942-1943
    - Attendees, list of (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - Cadre training (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - Kosciuszko Radio Station (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - Materials from Kuibyshev (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - Notes (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Party strategy (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Polish communist couriers (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Political discussion (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - European communist parties - conference plans, 1947 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Instytut Kształcenia Kadr Naukowych KC PZPR - theoretical conference, 1950-1952 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Komunistyczna Partia Polski (Communist Party of Poland) - release of members from prisons and rehabilitation, 1977 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Nowe Widnokregi, 1943 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Polska Zjednoczona Partia Robotnicza (Polish United Workers Party)
    - Educational policy
      - General, 1948-1953 (Box-folder 2: 2)
      - Conference on schoolbooks, 1953 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Membership statistics, 1949-1954 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Political Bureau, resignation from, 1955 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Polski Komitet Narodowy - resolution, 1941 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Skoniecki, Czeslaw, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - World Congress of Intellectuals for Peace, Wroclaw - notes, 1948 (Box-folder 2: 8)
- Writings and Speeches
  - General
    - 1946 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - 1947 (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - 1948 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    - 1949 (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - 1951 (Box-folder 2: 13)
    - 1952 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Bolshevik revolution, 1950 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - European countries of people's democracy, 1951 (Box-folder 2: 16)
- Photographs
  - General (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Trip to China (Box-folder 2: 18)